<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:tei_corpus.rnc" type="compact"?>-->
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en-Latn">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The digital Monier-Williams Sanskrit-English dictionary: XML edition.</title>
        <editor>Peter M. Scharf</editor>
        <editor>Thomas Malten</editor>
        <editor>Jim Funderburk</editor>
        <principal>Peter M. Scharf</principal>
        <funder>United States National Science Foundation</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>xml version, <date>2008</date></edition>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>markup analysis</resp>
          <name>Malcolm D. Hyman</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>lexical categorization of nominals, and feminine stem analysis</resp>
          <name>Ramaswamy Chandrashekar</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Greek data entry</resp>
          <name>Wendy Teo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>tagging of the list of works and authors, and association of abbreviations actually used with those in the list</resp>
          <name>Susan J. Moore</name>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>69.5 MB</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Sanskrit Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Providence, RI</pubPlace>
        <publisher>International Institute of Tamil Studies, University of Cologne</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Köln</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009">2009</date>
        <availability><p>All rights reserved other than those granted under the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial Share Alike license available in full at <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/legalcode"/>, and summarized at <ptr target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/"/>.  Permission is granted to build upon this work non-commercially, as long as credit is explicitly acknowledged exactly as described herein and derivative work is distributed under the same license.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">Sanskrit Library Lexical Sources</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>edited by</resp>
          <name>Peter M. Scharf</name>
        </respStmt>
        <idno>1</idno>
      </seriesStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>This work was supported in part by the United States National Science Foundation (NSF) under grant no. 0535207. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the views of the NSF.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct xml:id="MW">
          <monogr>
            <author>Monier-Williams, Monier</author>
            <author>Ernst Leumann</author>
            <author>Carl Cappeller</author>
            <title type="main" level="m">A Sanskrit-English Dictionary</title>
            <title type="subordinate" level="m">Etymologically and philologically arranged with special reference to cognate Indo-European languages</title>
            <edition>New edition, greatly enlarged and improved</edition>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
              <publisher>The Clarendon Press</publisher>
              <date>1899</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>xxxiv, [2], 1333 p.; 31cm.</extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <biblStruct xml:id="MWK">
          <monogr>
            <title type="main" level="m">The digital Monier-Williams Sanskrit-English dictionary</title>
            <edition>First digital edition</edition>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>Köln</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Köln Universität</publisher>
              <date>1997</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>26.4 MB</extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <!--projectDesc (project description) describes in detail the aim or purpose for which an electronic file was encoded, together with any other relevant information concerning the process by which it was assembled or collected.-->
      <projectDesc>
        <p><quote>The Cologne Digital Sanskrit Lexicon (CDSL) project undertakes to digitize and merge the major bilingual Sanskrit dictionaries compiled in the 19th century. Its aim is to provide a basic lexical corpus to provide an easy access to all available meanings of Sanskrit words and to allow the creation of a number of computer programs that will help to analyze Sanskrit texts. <bibl><author>Malten</author><date>1997</date><title>Review of the Cologne Digital Sanskrit Lexicon project</title></bibl></quote></p>
        <p><quote>In order to analyze forms in Sanskrit texts a parser must be combined with a database of lexical stems. The lexical sources described above in section III should be sufficient for producing the lexical component of a basic morphological analyzer/generator for Sanskrit.</quote></p>
        <p><quote>With a completed lexical database and morphological generator, it is possible to produce a full-form lexicon of Sanskrit, which maps every surface form onto a tuple (L, M), where L is a lexical base and M is a set of morphosyntactic features. Morphosyntactic features are indicated in accordance with the morphological tagging scheme published by Scharf.<bibl><author>Scharf</author><date>2005</date><title>International Digital Sanskrit Library Integration NEH project proposal</title></bibl></quote></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>xml version, <date>2008</date>, includes the designation of the fourth line of headwords; segregation of lexically significant sense text-extents between semicolons from those not lexically significant; designation of loanwords; designation of Sanskrit words in Anglicized Sanskrit encoding, markup of botanical and scientific terms; addition of lexical information required for proper inflection such as designation as indeclinable, pronoun, or comparative adjective; distinction of inflectional data from lexical data, specification of the scope of lexical and literary source tags; data-entry of Greek cognates; tagging of the list of works and authors, and association of abbreviations actually used with those in the list.<ptr target="http://www.sanskrit-lexicon.uni-koeln.de/talkMay2008/markingMonier.html"/></p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <!--"http://www.sanskrit-lexicon.uni-koeln.de/talkMay2008/mwtags.html"-->
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <creation>The original digital Monier Williams was created under the direction of Thomas Malten and entered by typists in <placeName>Azhivaikkal</placeName> in <placeName>Thanjavur district</placeName>, <placeName>Tamilnadu</placeName>, with character codes partially marking divisions in the text.  <persName>Scharf</persName> and <persName>Funderburk</persName>, with the assistance of <persName>Hyman</persName> and <persName>Chandrashekar</persName>, analyzed the existing markup, transformed it to xml, disambiguated it, and extended it.  Corrections were evaluated by <persName>Malten</persName>, <persName>Scharf</persName>, or <persName>Chandrashekar</persName> and implemented by <persName>Funderburk</persName>.</creation>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="sa-Latn-x-SLP1">Sanskrit</language>
        <language ident="grc-Latn-x-beta">Greek</language>
        <language ident="en-Latn">English</language>
        <language ident="sa-Latn-x-AS">Sanskrit</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#lcsh">
          <list>
            <item>Sanskrit language -- Dictionaries -- English</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <classCode scheme="#lc">PK933 .M6 1899</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>Revisions  documented by Jim Funderburk.  See <ptr target="http://www.sanskrit-lexicon.uni-koeln.de/talkMay2008/mwtags.html"/></change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <graphic url="http://www.sanskrit-lexicon.uni-koeln.de/cgi-bin/monier/serveimg.pl?file=/scans/MWScan/MWScanjpg/mw0001-a.jpg"/>
    <graphic url="http://www.sanskrit-lexicon.uni-koeln.de/cgi-bin/monier/serveimg.pl?file=/scans/MWScan/MWScanjpg/mw0002-akarman.jpg"/>
  </facsimile>

  <text>
    <body>
      <xi:include href="monier.xml">
        <xi:fallback>
          <p>Supply pointer to the contents of monier.xml here.</p>
        </xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
      <xi:include href="mwworksauthors.xml">
        <xi:fallback>
          <p>Supply pointer to a file the contents of front matter not in monier.xml here.</p>
        </xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
